so
so what I'm going to do today is
actually preview
a talk that I put together for the fifth
session of a
physics of information class that I'm
doing online for the active Insurance
Institute
and
um
this session's on SpaceTime and I wanted
to do this here for a couple of reasons
uh reason number one is
this uh particular session contains a
um
kind of hypothesis about biological
systems that I wanted to bounce off this
group
and the second one is that uh the
question of where space-time comes from
is I think particularly relevant in
biology and I think we can turn it into
a single biological question as well as
a developmental biological question
and even a developmental psychological
question
and so I wanted to sort of throw those
ideas around and see what people find
thank you so
a real Brief Review of
where we've gotten to in this class that
I know 100 L was in and and the rest of
you are maybe in
um
it's it's a class about Quantum
information Theory and this is a super
simple
model system for thinking about uh
communication between entities
um
we can think of of two entities which
together comprise the entire universe of
Interest so we can think of these two
digitizens jointly isolated
and the theory is just a general way to
describe how these entities
exchange information over some mutual
ability
so
um this whole approach to quantum theory
is based on information exchange across
boundaries and it turns out to me a
really kind of
powerful thinking tool
for thinking about how communication
constrains the structure of systems
so we can think of of the boundary as of
an information channel that has a
particular structure
and since we're using quantum theory we
can think about as as comprising some
array of qubits so quite a bits that can
be measured or prepared by either system
and talk about how that happens
um we're doing this in part to
understand the free energy principle
better
and so a couple of years ago Mike and
Carl friston and some other colleagues
and I put together a paper I think
actually it was just Jim glazebra
reformulating the free energy principle
in Quantum theoretic language
and if you reformulate it that way then
uh one can show that the free energy
principle is actually a classical limit
of the principle of unitarity which is
just the principle of conservation of
information
and the principle of unitarity is the
fundamental principle of planetary so it
makes the free energy principle kind of
naturally fall out of just the
assumption that you can describe the
world with quantitative which is kind of
a nice result because it makes the free
energy principle look less strange
and Carl's done a lot of work showing
that uh the free energy principle
provides you with a foundation for all
of classical physics
so
um relating it to Quantum Theory kind of
closes an important move there
and one thing that it does
is
automatically induced
compartmentalization
in any communicating systems that are
interesting in a very specific sense
well
it induces compartmentalization
whenever an agent has multiple ways of
interacting with the world and it can't
deploy them simultaneously for whatever
reason
so maybe it can't deploy them for some
kind of deep physical reason
um like you can't measure spin along the
z-axis and the x-axis at the same time
because those operations don't commute
automatically but it may be that it
can't deploy the simultaneously for a
much more prosaic reason it doesn't have
enough free energy
to thermodynamic freezers in the field
to both do this and this so it has to
have some attention system it says I can
act on the world this way or I can act
on the world this way but I don't have
the ability to do both so even that very
classical energy limitation on whether
systems can be deployed simultaneously
induces this kind of important
organization
and as soon as you have
compartmentalization between ways of
interacting with the world
you have to have some way of managing
what you're going to do so you you kind
of automatically induce a meta
processing system that attention system
and energy regulation system
just by the demands of not being able to
do everything all at once
so the the physics kind of bought by
itself gives you some interesting and
out of a few people
that one can then ask
um how how is that implemented even if
the cell biology level
and that so it provides a different way
of approaching cell biology
that's driven not by the chemistry
but by
the kinds of computations that the cell
has implemented we were talking earlier
at the lunch table or whatever it is
about
you know how do you take this horrible
spaghetti mess that's the pathway
diagram for a cell
that abstracts out all of the
interesting geometric constraints and
time constraints and that sort of thing
from the inside of the cell
and turn it into
some sort of compartmentalized structure
that tells you where the where the
borders are within that mess
where the cells have to exchange
classical information in some data
structures so in effect where the apis
inside the cell
um which is a kind of question that
doesn't naturally arise in other
representations
so just to make sure that I'm on the
same page the compartmentalization you
show here like green orange red
the green and the red would be Alice and
Bob in your initial uh
uh example are there two separate green
and red are the two compartments or any
two compartments or separate entities
that need to exchange information
classically through your qubit right now
right okay except with respect to the
original green and red are different
compartments and owls
okay and they're both looking at Bob
who's on the other side of America I see
okay so actually the next question could
you also reform it such that instead if
green and red were inside of Alice could
you also think about the Alice of Bob in
this case like this as long as they're
talking to somebody else okay right so
actually let me show you the next one oh
okay
oh you can
reformulate that diagram in a simpler
what
so here what I've done is green and red
are now q1 and Q2 these are two
important processes acting within some
overall computer with their distinct
Quantum processes so they have to be
compartmentalized in the way that it was
before
and
um
you can use this kind of picture
to represent two agents interacting with
a common environment
that are employing both a classical
channel so they're talking to each other
in language
and their
both measuring
some shared Quantum system
and this is exactly what happens in all
experiments that deterior and in fact
this is the minimal organization to be
able to detect entertainment
so it's the it's the the
kind of bottom line comment is that in
order to detect entanglement you have to
have classical communication
and so at the very it's a very depth of
all of quantum information technology
is a requirement for a kind of
communication that isn't Quantum
communication it's classical
communication
because I think of breaking into short
term taking a big messes lots of you
know lots of communication and lots of
stuff flowing around inside of a cell
and trying to break it into like you
were saying before that that sort of
Chunk size apis that communicate over a
somewhat minimal amount of of you know
wired signals
doesn't sound like a Quantum problem to
me so how does that how does all the the
the mechanism the formulas of the plot
the mechanics help
um
I just totally misunderstanding
well no I'm using the quantum formalism
as a particularly simple way of talking
about communication
but the other thing it gives to you is a
localization of thermodynamic
requirements
and so a localization of thermodynamics
free energy requirements to only the
places where you're encoding classical
information
so one motivation for doing this is this
analysis that Mike and I did a few years
ago
of
to what extent can you represent
the state changes inside a cell and in
particular protein conservational
changes as classical computation
in the way that they're actually
represented in say classical molecular
genetic simulations where you think of
proteins as sort of exploring this this
configuration of State space
and it turns out that cells
lack the free energy resources to do
that by orders of magnitude
so they
have to be using some other resource
some you know coherence resource that's
energetic and free to do some of this
computation
so one question motivated by that is
where do they have to store Quantum
information or where sorry where do they
have to exchange classical information
that really is energetically expensive
and that they really do have to put a
lot of resources into
and so they're they're kind of obvious
answers in the cell you know wherever
proteins are bound to a membrane
they're transmitting of classical State
across the memory to whatever
information processes that's happening
on the other side
um
that they're probably other boundaries
that we can't see just by looking at say
an electron micrograph
with their classical apis but at least
it raises that question where are the
apis inside
you know and how can we cut this up into
modules that we know have to communicate
by some sort of classical
information Exchange
given that can't be happy
so anyway
um
so that's just a very brief summary of
Where we've been
in this now multi-month course and now
we're finally to
um some of the part that's really
biologically interesting
to do with space
but
before I talk about space time and this
is actually motivated by questions
were asked after one of the other
sessions and Mike seems so what is
immediately to follow before because I
shared some of the previous meeting it
was the last few days
I wanted to talk a little bit about the
explanation
because it raises it an interesting
question about the scale dependence of
biological processes
so let's start by
contrasting uh
reductionist and scale from theories so
um the sorts of
approaches that we learned in
undergraduate school
in undergraduate physics and chemistry
for example
you know there's stuff going on at the
molecular level and the stuff going on
at the cellular level is just some
emergent process from all of that
chemistry
um
with a scale free type of theory like
does theory underlying this undulated by
the free energy principle which is a
scale free description of how systems
of any type communicating with their
environments and build models of their
environments and behave in their
environments
so in
any kind of reduction is theory
the basic idea is the explanation all
the all the real the important stuff
handles happens at some preferred state
and whatever's happening at larger
scales is emergent or LP phenomenal or
something like that it's you know it
doesn't matter at all
or
it's some sort of Packaging of what's
happening at the lower space
and
so the fundamental assumption is that
there's a fundamental skill
which that's most important
whereas in a scale free Theory
of the approach is very different skills
three Theory positive rates that there's
some kind of Dynamics
and that Dynamics happens at every scale
right yeah
and as you move between scales what
you're seeing are different
implementations at the same Theory
so it's a very different way of thinking
about Theory
and I would suggest that a lot of
science is actually not reductionist
even though scientists talk about it as
if it was rejections because I think
they learned extreme but they should say
and the scale-free approaches
kind of more difficult to think about
citizens
so if we go back to that picture of
systems talking to each other across the
boundary
and you ask about scale
then the way to represent scale is the
density of which information
and we can think about a whole spectrum
of scales
that are already given to us by physical
theory for example
energy scales or space spatial scales
and temporal scales and all of those are
coupled together by invasive physics or
basic physical constraints
so the kind of smallest possible
physically definable scale is the plank
scale
um
where and
energy of about you know the 19th gdv so
219 billion electron volts
is uh
compressed into a spatial scale of 10 to
the minus 35 meters so that's that
defines the boundary of a black hole
basically anything that includes
information at that scale is a black
hole
and 10 to the 19th gev it was you know
what is it
um
about 15 orders of magnitude larger than
the energy density that we can get with
the Large Hadron Collider
so it's a very high energy density
compared to what we could produce in the
laboratory
so the scale about one GED is the scale
at which nucleons exist and that
corresponds to a distance scale we're
about two minute minus 50 meters so
nucleons about 10 20 degrees size
um and our scale our natural scale is
about meter
and the associated energy is very low
that's radio frequency energy
so if you think about white
about 10 to the fifth higher energy than
radio waves so light feels energetic to
us
and radio waves don't
and that's just a fact about our size
that white seems very energetic compared
to something I created
which is our natural skill
so we can think about the boundary as as
encoding this information practically
different skills so now how do we feel
about science
and we're all familiar with with uh
kind of reduction in science where we
assume the fundamental scale and this is
the best example
right you have some event that happens
at some incredibly tiny scale in space
and time and very high energy
and that sets all the parameters for all
the physics and produces all the
organized structure that we see in our
work
I imagine
and that's called The Big Bang Theory
so the Big Bang Theory is is in a sense
the ultimate reductionist theory that
says that all of the important
parameters that characterize everything
are up to
boys
and nothing else
fixed up
the plant energy the plank Time by
spatial skill and everything else just
happens
so what we're looking for is a way of
thinking about science and scientific
explanation it's different from that
and it's hard to find an example that
with this sort of nice Illustrated
picture
so we have to draw a picture
and in the kind of notation we've used
here
um the picture looks sort of like this
we've got this system and the other side
of the boundary
and that system is changing
through some kind of God's eye type
record
and we're looking at our system Alice is
looking at the boundary
where else can see encoding is the
different scales
and let's call those scales one and two
and what's happening on the boundary at
these different scales is changing
so if Alice looks at
with you know magnifying glass that sees
scale number one
then she sees some changing pattern bits
now she works with a different
magnifying glass it seems scale number
two
she sees some changing pattern of goods
and she can construct a theory about how
these bits change over time
and that could be for example some
Markov process that captures the theory
and then the interesting question is how
do those two like
so can you construct
a saviente theory
embedding Theory
that says okay
bit patterns at this scale have some
correlation
and there's some part of the correlation
structure that's this sorry small scale
that matches the behavior of individual
bits at this very large scale so I
construct some sort of
if you will with it now
the language that seems natural at this
field and all I use this International
intensity
and it's how those theories change
through time that's a really interesting
question and you like your these
semantic backings to stay fixed because
then you know what you're talking about
as you progress through time to make
these different types of measures
so this picture should look familiar
because this is how computer science
works yeah and so we can
translate all this into to the language
of computer science now the scales of
different programs
um which may be things like an operating
system versus user interface versus what
we call the hardware level which really
isn't the hardware level it's a high
level description but a bunch of stuff
is doing
we can keep going down in space
with a laptop or something other scale
is kind of these are interface here
but what we're doing in Computer
Sciences constructing exactly this kind
of selectric value
between different ways of describing one
process
and we do that by assigning meanings and
mapping those meetings into each other
so that's why I call it a semantic
happened
and
um
with
computers
we design them so that the technical so
you know I talked about the relationship
between
you know the C compiler
so
HTML or something
in a way that doesn't change
so
what we can then ask is
and here's the
where we start to get into biology
uh what's the actual relationship
between these embedding theories in
biology
if you think about biology in this
scale-free way
which if we think in a free energy
principal framework we're doing
oh
then we can ask
what the embedding theories look like as
we go from thinking about how we have
the pathways into cells
cells in the tissues and tissues of
organisms or organisms and social works
and communities and what all the way up
to the biosphere but we have all these
different things
and this gives us a set of scale
transitions
and if we want to represent
sets of scale transitions we can turn to
again mathematical formalism and
representatives and renormalization
which is just a set of operators that
move things between different scales
and we can ask how different do these
transitions between different skills
and so I'll just put on the table a
hypothesis to think about
which is the hypothesis in the
biological systems those scale
transitions all look like the same thing
they're all formulated
and I don't know whether that's true
I don't even know how to approach trying
to prove that it's true or not true but
if it was true it would be really cool
because if you think that the theory was
super super simple
you'd have the free energy principle and
one scale operator
and with that you could do all the
events
so I'll just leave that there's
something to think about
um but be that is May we've done
something really important here
which is we've linked physics to
computer science
and we've done it in a way that
[Music]
um
is not just pre-constructing service
some God's eye view of physics with
computer science
we're trying to construct physics from
the point of view the embedded agent
in a way that that looks like computer
science and that immediately raises a
problem which is self-reference and we
know where that gets it gets you to
girls there
under very very general assumptions
so uh girdle warns us that this theory
is going to end up not being both
consistent
um
[Music]
so
um that's that's the end of part one
um now what I want to do is actually
talk about space
and do it from this kind of
scale free perspective
so ask a question yeah on that last
slide your what is the semantics level
It's Magic mapping on a computer it's
like we have programs that are actually
basically mapping that output
some interpretation of the hardware
other semantics and other programs like
mapping what was that house
looking at the program what
well
um think about processes like variable
binding
right as as soon as you get up to a
language where you can talk about
variable marketing
um if
if I have a variable and I'm binding
some some structure to it
and I can also bind that variable to
other kinds of structures
then we can think about what that
structure means to me
I have some some
notion of what two means reasonably
but
from the point of view of the program
of at least two means something
different from three
because if if I find a variable or two
then I do something different
if I'm buying the variable three
and the basis of semantics you know go
back to Gregory basin
is if if there's if there's a difference
that makes a difference to me that's
invincing substance actionable
That's the basis of semantics
it's the basis of meaningfulness
so you have some at least minimal sense
of meaningfulness
because as soon as you have variables a
distinction between variables and
constants
and you have one structure that that
leads to different actions a new
different circumstances
um
so the other the other way to think of
it is
when we are
describing what programs you're doing
we are naturally ascribing this and I
did through the program
so we're imposing a model Theory
in formal terms on this bunch of syntax
on this language
and when we look at different kinds of
languages we put very different model
theories on top of them
so the language is
you know
naturally have different instructions
it was a model theories we use or
typically very very different
so it's that's very strict down versions
referred to
and
there is some voices in computer science
that don't have distinction between
software and hardware and and I'm asking
that because here do you require that
the hardware should be a universal
tuning machine or no so it can be any
emulator
so I mean if we look at biology it's all
Hardware right since
um yeah it's just
we're we're describing the hardware of
different scales and we're building the
hardware right as we go
nuts that's even more strong statement
if the
how to should not be not necessarily
need to be Universal yeah
I mean I in a sense if you if you take
this
informational information Theory way of
thinking about physics
right seriously you get you know back to
the grandfather John Wheeler
and this Proclamation that physics is
information Theory
so Hardware is software right
and that
underlies a lot of that's much of the
underlying philosophy of this whole
transition that's occurred in quantity
or in the last 30 years
what's happening what's that like that
John Archibald wheeler
who was
an associate Baltimore and Einstein so
he kind of combined their different ways
of thinking and he was the
person you sort of
I think he came up with the name black
hole
he was part of that to me
Rebirth of general relativity in the
late 60s and in the next six weeks
and
um
go to a sequence of papers that can be
seen as the founding papers of
qualification
motivated a lot of those people who were
working early on in that area
okay so let's talk about space time and
really easy place to start because one
of wheelers
it was you have to start physics without
space-time figure out where Spaceman
comes from so there's the massive
departure from the kind of Einstein
viewed space-time is a physical
fundament even though
my son also said from a philosophical
point of States like this
that is somehow observed
so this notion of space finding Observer
relative
runs deeply through current Quantum
cosmology
so let's think about space
and let's think first about
absolutely uniform environment nothing
that's happened
but so I look at the environment
and none of it looks any different to me
and nothing's going on
so now I'm in general
yeah boundaries it's not all the same
yeah
so so this is where I want to start
and
um an organism that's living in an
environment like this is obviously not
an organism and not living
um because nothing's going on in this
environment but we can think of this as
an abstraction okay how do I build up a
meaningful environment from this
and how do I start putting a space-time
on how do I put some sort of coordinate
system on this environment so that I can
tell about you know what's going on over
there
so the first thing that you've got to do
is somehow segment the environment in
the parts that are different
so let's say that we can start to
segment the environment
so that at least different parts of it
look different even if nothing is
happening
so we have some part of the environment
what's different from some other part of
the theme park
but
now we can ask
is there any sense of of relationship
between these parts and obviously the
way that I've drawn it
um visually to us there's a relationship
but I haven't said that there's a
relationship
so right now actually I just have an
environment that's a set of two parts
and we can make it a little bit more
explicit by going to Four Points
so at the top I just have a set of
segments
and I haven't said anything about
what segment is next
for example even though visually I
obviously
wireless access
you can just think of this as a here
or a pile
so
I can take this set
and I can add some structure to it by
adding some topology
and the simplest thing to add to it is
some kind of graph structure
so I say okay this piece is next to this
piece this piece is next to this piece
Etc so I can take this and turn into a
graph
and I've drawn the little connections as
if they were Gap Junctions to sort of
suggest something about it planes of
cells that can talk to each other and
they know that they know they have a
neighbor
um there's some cells they can talk to
and other cells that they can't talk to
so they don't know anything about
so now
um there's still nothing happening even
though the environment has a little bit
of topological structure
but once you have some topological
structure once you you have more than
just a set of distinctions you know the
structures of distortions
we could talk about something happening
so let's talk about something really
simple simple
um there's
something happens in part of the
environment
and then something happens in some other
part of the environment
and I can tell these parts of the
environment are distinct
because I I've broken this symmetry that
allows me to move the parts of the
environment around by making some things
connected and other things not connected
so we can represent this in
a really simple way we can say in
the top panel there
uh a black dot has appeared in the white
green Square
and I represent this by an up arrow and
a green subscript and a black dot and
this is this is actually the notation
one uses in farm field Theory
so one can think of this as a what's
called a raising operator which just
creates a field excitation in the green
part of the field
and what it creates is this black dot
and then we can think of a different
state where black dot is disappeared
from the green part of the field the
white green bit and has appeared in the
yeah
dark blue there
so that's a representation of something
happening
and these black dots are now kind of
excitations of
a kind of field look included blackouts
so they're not yet objects in an
intuitive sense
their objects in the way that say
electrons are objects
where if I have if an electron appears
over here and an electron appears over
there from out of the quantum vacuum
then
the question of is this the same
electronics that never arises it's not
even a meaningful question
they have exactly the same properties of
their location
but
whether the account is the very same
thing is is a meaningless question
so at this level of description that's
to the meaning of this question
so we have a space where something's
happening that you can't there's no
sense of
there being an object in this ratio
but even in this really very simple
simple system
you can think about uh an observer
that has enough memory
to keep track of this sort of thing
happening over an extended period of
time
so an extended internal period of time
because that's with respect to some
internal memory of your consequence
so if you've got that kind of multi-step
memory
you can see State transitions like this
where something happens in part of your
environment and then something happens
in another part of your environment
something happens in the first part
something happens in the second part
and anytime you have that kind of
periodic Behavior
that's a clock in your environment
and it's a talk because you have enough
memory to see periodic Behavior
so you have that much memory you have to
have an internal counter that counts
experiences and labels them in your
memory
so I can say oh I've seen that state
before
as you can say I've seen that state
before and you can watch quite a few of
them and you have this kind of periodic
name
a clock
so notice what this does it does not
require
you can define a clock in your
environment
if you have distinguishable environment
sectors that have some topology that
prevents them from being arbitrarily
exchangeable
so you've got these connections you've
got this graph structure
you need some kind of flip-flop that's
implemented
on that structure
and you have to remember
but it doesn't require objective
we've implemented it just with this
Quantum field theoretic notion of events
happening in one place that are
happening in another place
and you don't have to have a metric
space
you don't have to have any sense of
distance
so you've got a really really minimal
structure on yours facials
representation of your environment but
you now have a nice external time
reference
uh that you can look at other events
with respect to
so this tells us something really
important I think for biology which is
that time is more fundamental respects
we can expect organisms
um even single cells to be able to
measure time in their environments
before
we can expect to see the measuring space
within their environments
and you know organisms that we know
about have things like diagonal Cycles
even bacteria the
we don't have any real reason to believe
impose a geometric structure on their
environments
even though
even bacteria distinguish sort of part
of their number
because the whole way that bacteria you
know Implement chemotaxis that's just
what you said they're they're so they
want to look towards gradient but
they're so small that one side of their
body and the other side of their body
are at the same concentration for all
practical purposes they cannot measure a
gradient in space they measure it in
time because that's what works yeah
and even before bacteria I mean
movements can can later write first
organisms to move much that makes all
the sense and at least I don't right now
and truly can guess how you would
measure space that movement it's going
to be probably possible for some like
light diffraction patterns but without
that um you know they can't move it's
gonna be way easier to measure because
there's a time of the environment to
somehow doing space
it makes sense that we're involved yeah
I would expect even that period you can
move
or even your Roblox that can move
may not be representing motion
so
they may not be representing objects
stuff that's more easy to represent
thesis
so so now let's think about representing
motion
um
I'm sorry can I can I ask a physics
related question sure how does this
relate to the esotropy of space because
if you compartmentalize space into
different cells
it does have need to have a certain kind
of uh well Arrangement so that light in
One Direction and in the diagonal
direction for instance takes the same
time to arrive at a certain distance
right
uh yeah let's get to that in a little
bit
I can talk about metrics
okay okay
I think that I think that's really a
metric question or almost a metric
question
okay let's think about
what do you need to observe motion
um what do you need to be able to say
that there's some object that's moving
around
so
um
suppose the I had this black dot
and it's it's exchanging its position
between light green and dark blue
but now I want to see that as motion
so see that as motion I need to add an
assumption
which is this this black dot
is not just a field excitation of some
Quantum field that's actually a thing
and what it means to be a thing is that
it persists through time it has some
identity Through Time so that I can say
that
when it's in the dark blue square it's
actually the same thing that used to be
in the white green Square
and that that same thing is going to
move now again at the end of the white
green Square
so object persistence
this this idea that I have a thing
is deeply deeply related to the notion
of translational invariance
which is one of the fundamental
symmetries that allowed you to define
the space the space time of the sword
that we have
so we have to make this extra assumption
that moving something doesn't change its
identity
and similarly moving something in this
space doesn't change the structure of
the space
so I have to make this assumption this
is part of translational experience
that if I move an object from here to
there I don't change the topology of the
space
where we don't have a geometry yet
so we have to assume that we still have
to assume that it doesn't can change the
connectivity structure in my space to
move something movable
so what I want to emphasize here is that
this notion of object persistence is a
classical idea
well it's it's not the idea that arises
naturally in Quantum filter
which says simply that something appears
something else appears that they have no
persistence
and
I think we can think about the entire
history of 80 years of interpretations
of quantums but you know
hundreds of books and thousands of
Articles written discussing metaphysics
basically
has all been really a debate about
object persistence and what the meaning
of object persistence
because as soon as you have problems
with persistence you made the transition
from a purely quantum theory to a theory
that's quantities
object persistence is what really
defines classical information it's I can
write a bit
I can write here and I can come back
tomorrow if I can read it
and there might be some noise
that often the noise it's the same bit
that I'm going to do it for That's a
classic car dude
so here's the quantity classical
transition it's the Assumption of object
persistence
I think it's worth thinking about where
that assumption comes from
Chris can I ask a question if you can
hear me
yeah
um so if you go back to the previous
slide uh could we also not in a sense
think of these sectors the green blue
sectors as also as things because they
persist even though they do not show any
motion could we not think of those
sectors also as things
because of resistance
I I
represented them this way
um
to to have a visual depiction
um but the the intuition I'm trying to
get across is
um
an intuition of of location or
distinction between different parts of
the environment
so we don't tend to think of you know
this little piece of space is an object
right
you know a little some little voxel
somewhere between me and the window
we just tend to think of that as as part
of our coordinates
so I've I've drawn it in this visual way
which suggests object to it
but you know the very uh kind of
a voxel in my space is really different
from something that I could put into
that box
so so this thing that I can move around
as an object whereas the kind of voxel
is an abstraction
so yeah I don't think they're the same
thing at all
I I guess uh I'm not an expert in
physics or relativity or but doesn't
Einstein's theory of space-time say
something about how space-time could be
deformed or marked or stretched and
contracted so doesn't it suggest that
space is also an object in effect
we'll get to that in a couple of slides
okay okay yeah hold hold your breath on
that one
so so I want to I want to talk a little
bit about object persistence more and
and just and and let us think about that
from kind of a developmental psychology
point of view this is how we learn about
object persistence
and we we get this about the first three
months
of infancy we do this kind of motor
babbling
and we do it with objects and we don't
have a a handy colorful thing
we just look at our own limbs
and notice what's happening here in this
picture of illustrates doing well
there's visual attention
and there's also motor attention
so what we're doing
when we're doing this motor babbling is
we're coupling a
somatosensially inappropriate safety of
representation of our body
with a visual representation of our body
and the visual representation is
assigning object Hood
to this thing that's otherwise a motor
representation
so what's a motor representation it's a
among other things is the amount of
energy I have to spend it's effortful to
do this and I can sense that effort
so and this is this is very indirectly
getting a percentage of this question
I'm starting to couple the ideas of
energy and object
by doing this sort of thing
and I'm also coupling it to the idea of
persistence over time
and manipulability
so these are deep deep
intuitions that we have
and uh I think we can say
just based on
physiological analogy as well as
behavioral analogy these are deep deep
intuitions that animals have
and maybe even the vertebrates have
so we can think about
space
pretty easily from the point of view of
second dog
uh and maybe even we can think about
space in the point of view of some frog
or a fish
um but
we don't have a good way of at least I
don't have a good way of thinking
intuitively pronunciation of point of
view something like an insect
it has a super different developmental
process than more
and isn't obvious in doing this kind of
process that was the process that taught
me what space was
so
uh I think we
we need to think about that when we're
thinking about space in terms of
biological systems so let's just in the
final segment here
think about what it takes to start to
impose a geometry on specs
so if I want to build a coordinate
system I want to build a geometry
in our area of motion
I need to have motion with respect to
something
so I need some sort of designated
preferred
position
but I can say okay I'm moving relative
to this
and as soon as I've got that I can start
to build some other invariances
so I can start to think about for
example rotational invariance
because now I can tell I'm rotating
because I can say okay this is
approaching but this is rotating
so now I can think about rotational
variance in the same way the thing about
translational variance
and if I want to think about
three-dimensional space
I can think about
kind of size
so if I if I move something it gets
smaller
and if I put it closer to here it gets
bigger I learned that when I was three
months old
because I had this mother getting ready
for me
um you can also think of that as as a
kind of energetic intervention
so if my object is over here I have to
spend energy to get to in a way that I
don't have to spend that energy if it's
right here
so you can think of this building this
third dimension in various ways
but you always have to have this origin
to build any kind of geometry
so once I have this I can also do
something really radical which is
Imagine like 20.
and uh I think it's an interesting
question to ask what animals are capable
of representing themselves
as opposed to representing their
environments is moving
and I don't know how to answer your
question I think it's a really
interesting question
so uh finally
I don't just need an origin if I want a
coordinate system I have to have a ruler
so I have to have a spatial reference
for
that consists of
this origin
and some will work
and my ruler has to be
um
translationally and rotationally and
very up to some transformation
and and here we get to the relationship
between say euclidean experience
where the ruler is invariant to
translations and rotations
um and and something like
um
space in general relativity where if I
move my ruler around it changes length
and if I rotate my rule of a chain
easily
and that length change is a
representation of mass in general
relative
Santosh was pointing out
so in fact it's it's not that this
space is a representation Beyond change
it's the change in the metric
that represents mass in general
relativity
so it's the way my ruler changes as I
move it
and that's a I think that's a very
interesting concept
which we'll talk about
so once I have these things once I have
the spatial reference frame
um
now I can talk about objects moving into
geometry
and I have what what we consider
intuitively in space so notice how much
more complicated this is than a clock
right simple to get a clock
that's really complicated to get this
space is a much more complicated notion
than than external time
okay
so we're almost done
um
I just want to think a little bit
abstractly now
and
interdisciplinarily now and think about
the approaches to emergency
I mean in the in the physics literature
especially Quantum information and to a
somewhat lesser extent under the rubric
of quantum cosmology
there's a large industry for
hundreds thousands of papers
uh they're working on emergent SpaceTime
and it's it's all an in a deeply
technical difficult language
and this route involves many many
variants on
starting from some sort of information
exchange and usually entanglement
and working through the idea of error
correction
uh in error correcting codes
and through the idea of lattice-like so
discrete Network types of topology
to get to some sort of space-time
and in particular by
always adding a bunch of different kinds
of assumptions to get to Einstein's
equations to to get to a space time that
supports some idea of
mass of gravity or energy density I mean
all of those are equivalent so some
sense of a metric that changes when you
do certain things
now there's a completely different
approach
which isn't expressed in incredibly
complicated mathematics
let's Express in the language you
developmental psychology
and
that way of thinking about space-time
starts with perceptual motor
capabilities so it starts from from
motor family
uh and it talks about the measurement of
effort
um
so it assigns an energy coordinate
at the top
and it talks about memory and it talks
about objects uh and invariances so
transcribe the ability to move something
around it and say this is the same thing
that I'm going to change
blah blah
and from there it builds this notion of
a metric space
and that metric space has a recent
implicit energetic coordinate that has
to do with distance
and
um it also has
sort of an energetic component that has
to do with mass so I know that there are
things in my space that require a lot
more effort to manipulate than other
things
but in in this way of thinking about it
that notion of effort
in mass is not really anchored in the
space it becomes a different Concept in
terms of this classical notion of mass
and the question is do these routes
eventually produce the same thing
and
the the sort of obvious answer is no
right the obvious answer is that uh
the left hand side
this this very recent you know two
decade two or three decade definitely
theoretical physics that starts moving
from string theory
how produces this this very abstract
notion of space that gives you Einsteins
equations
but is that really true
I mean one gets general relativity
just by thinking about symmetries in our
ordinary conception of space
that people haven't really focused on
for right Einstein really derived
general relativity from the equivalence
principle which is the idea that
acceleration and mass are the same did
it with all these thought experiments of
people in elevators and things like that
so in a sense general relativity follows
from our classical thinking about space
we noticed some symmetries that you
haven't noticed before
and you wrap some mathematics
so maybe these paths really do converge
and I think if they do converge it's
really interesting
um because it tells us something about
the relationship between physics and
biology
that I think is important
and
um what I I hope I
convention today is that there's at
least some possibility that maybe these
two paths really are leading to the
sense that really we can think about
constructing space time from an
organismal point of view
so I'll just leave you with one picture
which is a
organisms and babies and systems that
aren't organisms
managed to construct this cycle
from memory to object persistence to
error correction which I really haven't
talked about much again participation
um I'll just make one comment that that
space is really useful because it means
that I can I can correct errors again
put things in space and expect them to
be there
and that gives me an external memory so
I have space I have this converging
memory I have a whole lot of American
functions
I can use my ID card remember my name
oh so so organisms can do this
and that raises the question
which I think we can view as a
phylogenetic question
of how did this start
um where in phylogeny does this cycle
get going
and how does this cycle change in
different parts of phylogeny how do
different parts of phylogeny implement
the site and I think that's a really
interesting question in evolutionary
biology that's what we're thinking about
so I'll close with that thank you very
much
I'd like to build anyone
[Laughter]
so we're we're basically at one o'clock
so if there are a few questions that's
great
you my next step is to go to the airport
soon
you remember the experiment that's not
allowed to do today is
there is another experiment in that
category
there were some counselves that took
Keaton connected with a hinge together
Moon one of them it's a concept that
it's completely closed and there is
tribes in that car so and one kitten is
able to use these nerves and to move but
his movement affect the other kitten
that they folded and they're not allowed
him to use the legs and they they put
that kitten from from the beginning like
that
the result was that that kitten was
blind and there is nothing wrong with
that kitten only because he never used
his legs to close the loop with the
environment okay so his movement were
only completely not connected to him
it's the other cut so they released that
cut later on I don't remember exactly
the time numbers and the how many months
they put it there but they releasing and
they let him use the the the the legs
and he gets back his eyesight
so maybe that related to this kind of
thing yeah I bet no one can do that
experiment today but
yeah yeah working one can easily think
of experiments would be incredibly
informative and completely
certain importance
I like this because I I feel like yeah
this at the molecular level right and
and I think you can think of space as
being any area with less resistance
right so if you were to Define what
space is in this room most people would
say well it's the air right this is the
object whatever it has more resistance
but I think a molecule does this too
right because as molecule binds to
another atom and it changes it has a
memory of what it bound to and now you
have object persistence right because
now you have a different structure
there's changes the way the thing
interacts all the way through and it has
error correction because it doesn't bind
it it won't bind to a molecule that
doesn't have the right you know valence
electrons around it so you know once
that bumps into each other it will
reject it out and then it'll grab the
other one right so I think you're seeing
all this
you know not even organisms
right
next I mean yeah I would love to be able
to do
psychology
and really think about
um
these things as agents that are in some
sense common
yeah absolutely yeah we're all
crystalline lattices that's all we are
you know all the information that we're
transferring and thinking about all that
is being transferred through Crystal and
lattice yeah
so what will be the memory in that kind
of thing the structure
now the structural memory and
I think there's there's in a sense false
has converging them and the molecules
can
write on their environments in ways that
are persistent
and in ways they that they can go back
to and get information
at least I would have problems obvious
that molecules are doing that
certainly organisms are doing that all
the time yeah
it's a cool experiment in field mice
when they leave like literal markers on
the ground that are visually distinct
from the rest to remember where to go
you know
I mean the word
came originally from social insects or
memory of the environment
if we you know molecules using
stigmerging memories would be a super
cool result
but you can really nail it in here
makes me wonder if uh is
like a basic kind of foundation for
cognition you know when you mentioned
like you know basically all of biology
it is chemistry it's just physics
interactions based in most surveillance
of electrons
relationship between those two but
that's basically all the molecules too
and to extend positive and negative
charges both positive and negative
experiences
so so Mike's here is taking notes to
talk to Mark songs about this
yeah I think there's also good examples
of all the stuff that you could put
together with like systems Neuroscience
as well which speaks to your first point
of the scale free stuff right
it's probably all the same like I
I'd be more surprised if it was
people that I give up yeah
I think it's true
you came here to give this course
um well I came here to see who I haven't
beat people
are you standing around for a bit or do
you have to leave like right away from
the airport
yeah
okay can I ask a last question maybe an
iPhone
why is there three special dimensions
I'm sorry can I ask a naive question um
why is there three spatial dimensions
and not two or one for instance is there
a particular reason to that
oh
got those they're they're similar
medical facts about three space that
I've never been around that are real
interesting
yeah like building knots or something
like this I mean you cannot do
everything in two Dimensions or also in
one year but um but there are also
things that you can do in three
dimensions that you can't for example do
in four dimensions
ah like so a
um
you know four dimensions plus time
would be
uh would not allow certain symmetries
that we depend on too
um to kind of have some coherent notion
of objects
so and you know I'm sorry I don't
remember what these things are but uh
that's a really interesting question and
a lot of people work on it and
um an important part of it is is why
three not four or more and and three
turns out to have unique unique
geometric properties
that are really cool
so it when people talk about extra
dimensions and strength area or
something like that all the extras
facial Dimensions after we rolled up
into tiny little packages so that they
don't interfere with
with doing anything macroscopically
where macroscoplings you know above the
plank scale
yeah yeah this is really interesting
um also if it's about
um well distinguishing between objects
then also there's questions if space can
be continuous for instance because
making very very small changes in a
continuous
we won't lead you to different positions
right so
yeah this is where the the limitations
imposed by energy density really make a
difference
um
you know the playing scales tiny
but
um if you if you try to go to go beyond
that
the the energy densities are so high
that it
um
it sort of feels like you're getting big
again
um it's
again I don't have a good intuitive
grasp on that
but the the
existence of this energy distance
relationship
kind of gives you a fundamental
dissertation of space for free
and uh when you look at these Quantum
information types
they're they're all based in
five-dimensional over spaces
and there's been a huge transition away
from the kind of old quantum mechanics
where everything was done in continuous
over spaces to the much much simpler
representation of doing things and try
out dimensions
uh the downside of that it means that
that all of
continuous mathematics like differential
equations becomes an approximation on
the Dynamics that's
conceptually simpler but but from a
computational point of view much more
difficult
um
yeah it's it's really hard to grasp um I
I when I studied this stuff I always
imagine space time to be some kind of uh
automaton where you have like a little
space grids and uh well
communicating with each other with the
speed of light something like this that
being the clock time of the of the
automaton but it feels like it's much
more Dynamic and Space is really
emergent and more like a property you
assigned to
particles or anything that
distinguishes them from each other and
it allows you to build correlations on
top of other degrees of freedoms